Guide to the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company Records, 1860-1999 AIS.1982.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Monongahela Connecting Railroad, 1864-1919; III.
  - Correspondence pertaining to employee matters, embargoes, coal reports, information on coal run between Verta Mines and J&L Steel Co., car movements, and various of Frank McCune, General Superintendent, 1907-1918 (Box 349a)
  - Correspondence of Frank McCune, general superintendent, regarding all manner of railroad activity; Pittsburgh Textile Company bills; yardmaster, trainmen, and engine men meeting reports; Depression-era bulletins and advertisements, 1908-1931 (Box 349b)
  - Reports of coal reserves, recoverable coal at mines, freight survey (1931-34); Ashtabula and Shenango trackage rights agreements, contracts, and reports (1976-84); Union mediation agreements (90s), 1931-44; 1976-91 (Box 370)
  - Annual reports of the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie, Mahoning State Line, Monongahela Connecting, and Beaver & Ellwood railroads, 1901-1909 (Box 371)
  - 'Pink Sheets' generally Car Department, mostly written by H.C. Christie; Reports of Examination of MCRR and PC&Y; bound operation reports, income accounts, and general balance sheets, 1936-1985 (Box 444a)
  - Office of industrial engineering operations; iron ore movements; hopper and gondola studies; correspondence concerning Montour Junction auto ramp; Mahoning State Line Railroad study; Dravo Stone proposal, 1968-1980 (Box 476)
  - Monongahela Connecting Railroad 100th Anniversary collection of pen and ink drawings; report book for Pittsburgh, McKeesport, & Youghiogheny Railroad; right of way deeds, 1870-1925 (Box 529b)
  - Project envelopes for railroad improvements, 1966-1970 (Box 568)
- Montour Railroad, 1900-1995; IV.
  The Montour Railroad was chartered in 1877 as a short line railroad to haul coal from rural western Pennsylvania to the steel industry of Pittsburgh and beyond. The first segment constructed extended southward from Montour Junction (near Coraopolis, Pa.) to the town of Imperial, Pa. In 1912 the railroad underwent a major expansion, and by 1917 reached West Mifflin by way of McDonald, Cecil, and Bethel Park. It became an important link in the rail transportation system serving Pittsburgh, Youngstown, Oh., and Cleveland because it connected to all five of the trunk railroads serving the area. The Montour served 27 mines and carried almost seven million tons of coal annually by its peak in 1930. Other freight was virtually incidental, and passenger service was abandoned in the 1920s. In 1946 the Montour Railroad was sold jointly to the Pennsylvania Railroad and the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad. The P&LE acquired sole ownership in 1975. As costs continued to rise and revenues decrease, operations ceased entirely in 1984.
  This series is another which contains a wide breath of information for the understanding of how the company functioned on a day-to-day basis through its different departments and how it dealt with problems that arose. Included materials span from 1898 to 1995 and are related to general operations of the railroad, such as employee records and wages, annual reports, bulletins, equipment logs, litigation, and engineering records. There are also some case files and hearings relating to the Lake Erie and Ohio Canal in this series.
  - Engineering (Montour Railroad): Bridges, Bridge Inspection Under grade Reports (1968-78), McDonald Viaduct, Weed Program (1961-68), Mileage of Tracks Change in Track Reports (1961-76), Track Renewal and maintenance reports (1975-79), 1961-1979 (Box 77)
  - Research, publications, etc. concerning Coal and Coke Context in Pennsylvania, Early 1900s, 1950s, 1970s (Box 30)
  - Engineering (Montour Railroad): Bridges, Bridge Inspection Under grade Reports (1968-78), McDonald Viaduct, Weed Program (1961-68), Mileage of Tracks Change in Track Reports (1961-76), Track Renewal and maintenance reports (1975-79), 1961-1979 (Box 77)
  - Workers agreements - Clerks, Shop Crafts, Steelworkers, Engineers, Yardmasters, Trainmen, Engineers. Rules Governing Employees, 1981 (Box 131)
  - P&LE and Eastern Railroad Companies agreement, Engineering Files - Damage to Roadway During Flood (1937), Blueprints and Estimate of Cost and Correspondence (Airport Parkway), Engine logs Montour Railroad, 1930s-1940s (Box 134)
  - Engineering Department - 1956 Zoning Ordinance; files on Montour Railroad and Youngstown & Southern Railroad acquisitions; main line switch; City Planning reports; crossings; property purchases; articles of agreement, 1898-1958 (Box 218)
  - Engineering Department - Connellsville Western Maryland abandonments, Detroit Edison Trains, Montour Railroad champion terminal study, Penn Central use of Lake Erie & Eastern, Walford Branch, Ohio River Branch, 1980s (Box 221)
  - Employee records--out of service, 1917-1979 (Box 288a-288b)
  - Employee records--out of service, correspondence to Youngstown & Southern, Operating Revenues and costs, 1937-1987 (Box 288c)
  - Employees out of service, record index employee numbers for 1-1700 index of names, 1937-1974 (Box 297a)
  - Employees out of service; wage reports, 1899-1983 (Box 297b)
  - Employees out of service; post operation sales of railroad equipment; reports to Railroad retirement service; special account payroll (SPA numbers), 1938-1990 (Box 297c)
  - State road crossings, changes in grade crossings, properties secured, correspondence with other railroads, engineator wiring diagrams, parts including joints, transfers, and track fastenings, and matters of Montour Railroad and engineering department, 1913-1951 (Box 300b)
  - Tax Return Information, Gas Meter Readings, Automobile Insurance Records for Montour Railroad Company, Correspondence concerning scale tests, crossing gates, 1931-1985 (Box 326)
  - Legal matters: property titles, court hearings, payments, rental agreements, contracts etc., 1900-1959 (Box 338)
  - General Notice Index; Falcon Club Auction log (1999); Employment Procedures (1950s); meeting minutes; Montour Railroad Annual Reports to Interstate Commerce Commission; Management Employee Handbook of P railroad company agreement books for P&LE, Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad, and United Transportation Union, 1934-1999 (Box 355)
  - Annual Reports, 1920-1939 (Box 368)
  - Annual reports of Lake Erie & Eastern, Youngstown & Southern, Mahoning State Line, and Montour railroads, 1949-1979 (Box 377)
  - Maintenance of Way agreements; P&LE news bureau releases; stockholder meetings; vendor brochures; published annual reports; Montour agreements; irregularities and disciplines; Youngstown Superintendent Association meeting notes and correspondence, 1960s-1970s (Box 379)
  - Locomotive study; cabin and caboose car information; freight car classifications; abandonments; equipment and building requirements; leases; rentals; sales; authorizations, 1965-1991 (Box 380)
  - Land deeds between railroad and private land owners, 1913-1916 (Box 384a-384b)
  - Laws and litigation of Montour and Y&S closings; filed complaints; police commissions, 1942-1968 (Box 385a)
  - Board meeting, property inventory of worth, correspondence, Board of Directors meetings, Stockholder's meeting, 1965-1976 (Box 386)
  - Employee benefits files (health, dental, off-track vehicle accident); mines rating and production; Consol Energy vs. Montour docket; correspondence with Association of American Railroad, various federal agencies, and other railroads; company appointments; property permits; general orders and rule book changes, 1960-1983 (Box 388)
  - Stenographer's minutes for valuation of Montour Railroad, recovery and payment of excess operating income; waybills; legal matters of Montour Railroad such as agreements with Pittsburgh Coal Company and Union Trust Company of Pittsburgh and others, 1905-1950 (Box 389)
  - Matters of materials (such as coal, scrap, cars, etc.), 1980-1983 (Box 390)
  - Articles of agreement between Montour Railroad and various companies and contractors; work authorizations; multi-railroad agreement book on rules and rates of pay for trainmen and yardmen, 1904-1955 (Box 391a)
  - Notices and bulletins; correspondence with Consolidation Coal Company; locomotive inspection reports; demurrage sheets; locomotive and car repair sheets; P&L statements; bridge maintenance data; destruction of records, 1911-1980 (Box 391b)
  - Employee Social Security Registration Applications, 1900-1960s (Box 392a)
  - Montour car record cards; P&LE Office of Local Treasurer Corporate Cash Books microfilms, 1900-1983 (Box 392b)
  - Articles of agreement between Montour Railroad and various companies and contractors; track layouts on Neville Island; correspondence of PC&Y Railroad, 1900-1955 (Box 393a)
  - Correspondence of PC&Y Railroad, 1900-1995 (Box 393b)
  - Correspondence of Chief Engineer; construction contract for bridge, 1913-1914 (Box 394a)
  - Correspondence of Chief Engineer, to and from Pittsburgh & Lake Erie, regarding US government dam construction proposal, 1913-1940s (Box 394b)
  - Blueprints and engineering plans, 1950s (Box 395)
  - Records of employees from P&LE, 1950-1981 (Box 396)
  - Correspondence concerning notice of abandonment; various agreements; call sheets; coal mine reports, 1900-1982 (Box 397)
  - Deeds, 1900-1915 (Box 399a)
  - Annual Reports; miscellaneous papers and blueprints, 1884-1918 (Box 399b)
  - Rules and Rates of Pay; Railway Labor Act papers; case files of Lake Erie & Ohio River Canal project hearings, 1936-1975 (Box 400a)
  - Case files of Lake Erie & Ohio River Canal project hearings, 1926-1939 (Box 400b)
  - Maintenance of way department bulletins; correspondence of engineering department; labor issues, 1964-1980 (Box 401)
  - New York Central Railway blueprints (1950s); agreements with Consolidation Coal Co (1935-47); correspondence concerning issues of the West Pittsburgh Station (1946-61), 1935-1961 (Box 402)
  - Correspondence concerning Flood Committee; sidetracks; maintenance and repair of diesel locomotives; study of Montour Railroad coal movements; joint facilities; flat car conversion design; centralized crew dispatching; cost analyses; Detroit-Edison train; hot slab trains; Aliquippa & Southern Railroad, 1897-1973 (Box 424)
  - Bound reports of operations, general balance sheets, and expenditure statements; Montour changes in equipment (1960-66); Carrier's Review of and comments concerning reports for property of PC&Y, 1920-1966 (Box 444b)
  - Crossing accidents, 1946-1982 (Box 448)
  - Reports and correspondence of CSX; P&LE phone directory; employee General Notices (1980s); union information; Montour and PC&Y, car service rules; Connellsville machinery, passenger cars, environmental concerns and correspondence; radios (1981-91); contract services provided by P agreements with CIO; TWU correspondence and reports; Employee Assistance Program booklet; claims against Montour Railroad, 1981-1992 (Box 467)
  - Meeting minutes, resolutions, government correspondence, leases, dockets, blueprints, etc., reporting the establishment of the Northern Montour Railroad Company; accident reports; application of Mingo Valley Railroad; articles of agreement between Montour Railroad Company and other railroads for consolidation and mergers; contracts between Montour and various companies, 1912-1920 (Box 484)
  - Deed from Pittsburgh Terminal Railroad Company to Montour (1919); locomotive replacement (1979); Interstate Commerce Commission briefs concerning valuations and construction (1927-29); construction agreements (1920s); Smith's Ferry Loading Boom construction (1920s); book of balance sheets (1914-17), 1920-1979 (Box 513)
  - Cars under obligation, gondola end modification; paperwork, pamphlets, catalogs, and instructions for various equipment and parts, 1976-1989 (Box 515)
  - Building costs booklet; daily locomotive performance records; valuation docket of Montour; train statistics of Interstate Commerce Commission; contracts; Montour - Y&S merger proposal; Bessemer & Lake Erie Railroad correspondence; policeman commissions; numerous loose blueprints, 1914-1994 (Box 516a)
  - Pricing schedule for track laying and surfacing; Pittsburgh - Chicago Dist. Cost Data Committee reports on Ballasts (1920); track laying and surfacing cost comparison; booklets on costs of: building, development, freight cars, grading, obtaining money, bridges; ICC valuation dockets; record of property changes, 1920s (Box 516b)
  - Shop maintenance standards (1986); multi-railroad agreements on car men, their helpers, and apprentices (1963); agreement between PA railroads and American Railway Supervisors Association (1957); master agreement for restructuring of obligations of P&LE (1985); various other multi-railroad agreements; Montour Railroad railway operating revenues (1927-1941), 1927-1986 (Box 517)
  - Court testimonies; railway operating revenues and statements of operations, 1899-1960 (Box 528)
  - Land purchase authorizations; deeds, 1910-1931 (Box 530)
  - Sale of Montour to Pittsburgh Coal; Montour pipe line crossings; construction blueprints; death investigation reports; legal issues; financial issues; applications for crossings and construction; land deeds; land trusts; requests among railroads for car returns; 1965 budget; job postings, 1913-1930 (Box 537)
  - Reports of coal weighed and stop off charges for Champion, Pa., 1965 (Box 539)
  - Personal injury summary cards of Montour Railroad employees; LE&E records book; notes on cross sections; LE&E and PL&E crossing agreements, 1922-1965 (Box 539)
  - Freight car ownership logs; maintenance of equipment and freight cars; sale orders; leased car file; terminal building development; re-stenciled cars; car retirement sheets; Montour and Youngstown & Southern Railroad monthly reports of revenue freight cars, 1970-1990 (Box 552a)
  - Log of detailed traffic statistics, 1940-1943 (Box 571)
  - ICC Bureau of Valuation land and engineering reports, including blueprints, 1917-1926 (Box 572)
  - Reports of waybills received from various companies, 1955 (Box 573)
  - Bound ledger of financial data, 1913-1928 (Oversize 574)
- New York Central System, 1905-1965; V.
  The New York Central Railroad operated in the northeastern United States. Headquartered in New York, the railroad served most of the Northeast, including extensive trackage in the states of New York, Pennsylvania, Ohio, Michigan, Indiana, Illinois and Massachusetts, plus additional trackage in the Canadian provinces of Ontario and Quebec. The railroad primarily connected greater New York and Boston in the east with Chicago and St. Louis in the midwest along with the intermediate cities of Albany, Buffalo, Cleveland, Cincinnati, and Detroit. The New York Central's Grand Central Terminal in New York City is one of its best known extant landmarks. In 1968 the New York Central merged with its former rival, the Pennsylvania Railroad, to form Penn Central. The Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad was operated by both the New York Central Railroad and Penn Central during their years of existence.
  The series is completely comprised of boxes containing bound annual reports of the New York Central Railroad. The reports include New York Central & Hudson River Railroad Co.; Lake Shore & Michigan Southern Railway Co.; Michigan Central Railroad Co.; Lake Erie & Western Railroad Co.; Indiana Illinois & Iowa Railroad Co.; Indiana Harbor Railroad Co.; Cleveland, Cincinnati, Chicago & St. Louis Railroad Co.; Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Co.; Rutland Railroad Co.; New York Central Railroad Co.; Mahoning Coal Railroad Co.; Toronto Hamilton & Buffalo Railway Co.; Peoria & Eastern Railway Co.; Central Union Depot & Railway Co. of Cincinnati. Not all of these railroads appear in every book, but they will appear somewhere in the books in this series. In addition, the reports list leased and controlled lines together with additional statistical financial and corporate information for the use of their officers.
  - New York Central Lines Athletic Associations Sixth Annual Track Meet to be Held At Pitt Stadium Sept. 18th 1929 (3586 FF8-1), Freight House Office Building Floor Plan (1785 JA3), The Monongahela Railway Showing Coal and Coke Operations (14193 - KF -12 and 209 - K - 393) (Box 137)
  - New York Central Railway blueprints (1950s) MCRR: Agreements with Consolidation Coal Co (1935-47); correspondence concerning issues of the West Pittsburgh Station (1946-61), 1935-1961 (Box 402)
  - New York Central Railroad System Annual Reports, 1905-1965 (Box 600-613)
- Pittsburgh, Chartiers & Youghiogheny Railroad, 1898-1995; VI.
  On May 26, 1892, the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company purchased one-half interest in the Pittsburgh, Chartiers & Youghiogheny Railroad Company. They negotiated a contract with the Pittsburgh Cincinnati Chicago & St. Louis Railway Company, which had also purchased one-half interest, for the operation of the road.
  The series holds a small amount of records for this railroad and its dealings with other companies as well as functioning of its engineering department. There is also mention of the Neville Island freight and the McKees Rocks station.
  - Pittsburgh Chartiers & Youghiogheny Railway Co. Damage papers McKees Rocks, Freight Car Shop McKees Rocks, etc., 1910-1950s (Box 213)
  - Old and Cancelled PC&Y 349-H to 349-N (Various sidetrack agreements), 1950s (Box 240)
  - Old and Cancelled PC&Y 312.22-D to 312.22-W (Duquesne Light Crossings at Chestnut Street, Kennedy and Guthrie Station, and Railroad Street), 1940s-1950s (Box 241)
  - Records of 1981 'Great Train Ride', contracts and agreements with Pennsylvania Railroad Company, study of Jones & Laughlin Steel Company, General Notices, track changes, matters of Pittsburgh, Chartiers & Youghiogheny Railroad Company and Gateway Yard, 1927-1984 (Box 296a)
  - Reports on purchases of Little Kanawha Syndicate Lines (1919-20); closing of PC&Y (1970s-80s); correspondence and reports of PC&Y Railroad, 1900-1983 (Box 392c)
  - Correspondence of PC&Y Railroad, 1900-1995 (Box 393b)
  - Correspondence concerning PC&Y; property issues, 1902-1960 (Box 398b)
  - Engineering issues of PC&Y and McKeesport station and Neville Island freight, 1933-1949 (Box 406)
  - Correspondence concerning McKees Rocks station: construction, maintenance; PC&Y railroad company papers concerning Neville Island freight, 1903-1956 (Box 409a)
  - Track construction and maintenance, 1909-1935 (Box 416)
  - Superintendent agreements (regarding sidetracks, wages, etc.); car records; J&L Steel contract on equipment transfer services; railroad company agreements; studies of billing, switching, and future procedures; various bills; changes in operating facilities at East Youngstown, OH; car sales records; contracts with PC&Y, 1939-1983 (Box 440a)
  - 'Pink Sheets' generally Car Department, mostly written by H.C. Christie; Reports of Examination of MCRR and PC&Y; bound operation reports, income accounts, and general balance sheets, 1936-1985 (Box 444a)
  - Bound reports of operations, general balance sheets, and expenditure statements; Montour changes in equipment (1960-66); Carrier's Review of and comments concerning reports for property of PC&Y, 1920-1966 (Box 444b)
  - Reports to the office of Chief Engineer from the American Railway Association, Interstate Commerce Commission, Pennsylvania Railroad Association, Eastern Railway Association, General Managers Association; information regarding industrial supplies and equipment; PC&Y: Employee medical reports, 1960-1991 (Box 488)
  - PC&Y annual reports of maintenance of way (1925-30); O.S. reports (1898-1943); Allegheny County record book; book of right of way deeds; train orders; flood planning information; Penn Central procedures for Capital Projects (1968); testimony of PLW President and Director, 1898-1968 (Box 534)
  - Log of project reports, accounts, and expenditures, 1916-1981 (Oversize 576)
- Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad, 1860-1999; VII.
  The Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad (P&LE) began operation in 1879 after the 1878 consolidation with the Youngstown & Pittsburgh Railroad Company. Headquartered in Pittsburgh, Pa., the P&LE line began as a single track railroad connecting Pittsburgh to Youngstown, Ohio. The railroad began its affiliation with the New York Central System in 1883 and, by 1890, was one of the principle rail routes in the eastern United States. As it grew, it became able to handle six times the amount of freight it had in 1880, earning its nickname, the "Little Giant." In 1879 the railroad became heavily used line by travelers and commuters. Eventually, the rise of motor trucks, private cars, and buses led to the decline of train travel, and by the mid-1970s, only one commuter train remained on the P&LE line.
  While the early 1970s brought a decline in passenger travel, the freight lines continued to grow. In 1976, following the 1970 bankruptcy of the Penn Central System, the railroad obtained trackage rights over former Penn Central lines to Ashtabula Harbor, Oh., located on Lake Erie and through Sharon to Shenango, Pennsylvania. The railroad was purchased by CSX Transportation in 1993.
  The materials in this series are further divided into subseries to give an outline of the functions and operations of the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad.
  - Engineering, 1850-1944; 1.
    Records in the collection pertaining to engineering are often explicitly labeled as such by the railroad. A large amount of these will be correspondence to and from the Chief Mechanical Engineer in addressing certain blueprints, as well as records of machinery, bridges, buildings, equipment, locomotives, and railroad cars.
    It should be noted that a significant number of boxes in this subseries contain information regarding the Ohio River and Lake Erie Canal, from the mouth of the Beaver River at Rochester, Pa., to a point near Ashtabula, Oh., on Lake Erie and came under discussion in 1930. Blueprints, studies, and many newspaper clippings create a record of this canal and highlight the interest Pittsburgh and its railroad industry had in this project which never took place.
    - Trainmen rosters (1980s), Bulletin Orders (1980s), Tax Assessments (1930), blueprints and work orders to Bethlehem Steel for rail cars and 250-ton steel wreck crane, 1930-1986 (Box 2)
    - Locomotive serial numbers and information files, 1930-1970 (Box 5)
    - Parts diagrams and blueprints and information, 1970s (Box 6)
    - Legal documents (land transfers, etc); Office of Engineer building specs for various equipment and implementation (ex. switches), 1915-1946 (Box 8)
    - Rail purchase, Robins Car Shakeout Installation/ Blueprints, Scale house and track scales construction, Dravosburg Bridge and Blue prints, flashing light RR crossing system, 1940s (Box 20)
    - Office of Chief Engineer legal files (suits, laws, and government acts), 1975-1980 (Box 25)
    - Car information files (cars damaged on foreign lines, cars sent home for repairs), 1980s (Box 28)
    - 5931 Rajah Oil Co. lease of property and side track, Lansingville and Youngstown Gas and Oil Co. lease of land and sidetrack (1919), 5931 Holub Iron & Steel Co. lease of land at Lansingville (1936), 5951 Pittsburgh & West Virginia Railway Connellsville (1919), 5995 Combustion Engineering Sidetrack-drainage a/c Combustion Engineering Company (1902), 5997-A Lease of Property at Groveton to William Duffy for camping (1924), 6030-A Pittsburgh Knife and Forge Company Siding Coraopolis (1919), 1902-1936 (Box 75)
    - Colona River Rail Transfer Plant (1932), Colona River Rail Transfer Plant Track Scale (1931), Colona River Rail Transfer Plant (1896-1927), Colona River Rail Transfer Plant (1930), Colona River Rail Transfer Plant Electric (1931), Colona River Rail Transfer Plant - Fixed Charges, reconditioning, dredging (1933), 1896-1933 (Box 76)